James Appleby

EDS Project Engineer at Draexlmaier UK

james.appleby1989@gmail.com

Summary

As an engineer responsible for a lead program on a new platform, I have experience in project management within the automotive industry and global supply base including a number of full and minor model changes. My experience within the industry has been further developed by my involvement with a number of OEM's and from interaction within the supply base (tier 1 and tier 2 suppliers).

My areas of main expertise are within the EDS, High Voltage and Quality functions. With an active understanding of development contracts as well as mass production and with the benefit of an understanding of both high voltage and low voltage wiring, I have pushed myself to become both experienced and well-rounded in my knowledge of these functions.

I am committed to continuous self development with a view to further developing my knowledge of project management within the engineering field. My ultimate aim being to achieve Chartered Engineer status within the IMechE/IEE.

Experience

EDS Project Engineer at DAU DRAEXLMAIER AUTOMOTIVE UK LIMITED

January 2015 - Present (2 years 3 months)

Reason for leaving – Production contract won by alternate supplier.

Duties included:

- Developing harness strategies for an electric vehicle
- Circuit development
- Requirement validation/verification

Project engineer responsible for harness and circuit development on an electric vehicle. In particular, my responsibilities focussed around the development of IP, Console and High Voltage Traction Battery development. Due to ownership and development of the High Voltage function being new to JLR, this has required the interpretation of JLR set requirements to be developed in such ways that they are applied to the new harness technology to ensure compliance.

As part of the role I have been expected to manage key roles within the drawing and manufacturing plants/ teams that make up the greater company. Assisting with the resolution of drawing and manufacturing related issues and communicating these issues with UK and international based teams to achieve tight milestones.

Further responsibilities stretched into circuit generation including circuit and device transmittal auditing, circuit error checking to ensure DSI release and the effective management of late change against a constantly slipping timing plan. With JLR repeatedly editing the device transmittals over a number of new devices, the need to ensure auditing, error checking and late change management are all done correctly and thoroughly has been particularly important.

EDS Launch Engineer at Lear Corporation

August 2014 - January 2015 (6 months)

Reason for leaving – End of contract due to successful vehicle launch.

Duties included:

- Issue management from root cause development to countermeasure verification
- Tracking of late change
- Day to day management of the rework team

As launch engineer for multiple programs it was important to be able to manage the issues raised from builds in a timely manner and to report this back to the customer in a clear and concise fashion. This meant checking harness drawings and circuit diagrams against actual vehicle conditions, suggesting changes where possible that would alleviate the issue and communicating this back to the appropriate engineering teams.

During this role I was required to manage the rework team and ensure rework was applied in a priority manner with all change management records kept up to date and clear so as to be sure reworks were carried out correctly.

Module Leader - EDS/Global Business Expansion Change Management at Jaguar Land Rover May 2013 - August 2014 (1 year 4 months)

Reason for leaving – seeking something more challenging/technical

Duties included:

- Developing change management processes/PLM systems locally and in preparation for international expansion.
- Project management of a lead program on a new platform
- Issue resolution from a cost, engineering and manufacturing feasibility perspective.

Employed as Module Leader for a lead program on a new platform my responsibilities included but were not limited to the management of costing, complexity, engineering, timing and issue resolution. The position has required a close working relationship with the harness supplier at all times and at all phases of the program from design to prototype production.

My time within JLR also required me to manage the development of new and existing processes both within the UK and international manufacturing including; engineering changes, feature change implementation, bill of materials and numerous other processes. The management of these processes was from concept generation through to engineer rollout.

A - E - Quality Project Leader at Honda of the UK Manufacturing Ltd.

May 2011 - May 2013 (2 years 1 month)

Reason for leaving – redundancy.

Duties included:

- Developing quality strategies
- High profile project management across multiple departments
- Development and implementation of new New Model Development Cycles including prototype and non-prototype.

Initially starting in the warranty section within Supplier Quality Development Division, dealing with tier 1 and tier 2 supplier related market quality concerns, I was responsible for managing the issues from root cause establishment to countermeasure verification. The global nature of the OEM supply base required me to work with suppliers locally and globally including frequent visits overseas

I was later requested to manage a supplier that was in significant difficulty and unable to control its quality level of produced parts. This required hands-on day to day management of the supplier. As acting quality manager I was involved in every aspect of the supplier from build plans and gemba management to quality strategies/concern resolution.

After 10 months service at Honda of the UK Manufacturing I was moved to New Model Supplier Development where I was responsible for a number of suppliers producing complex parts such as driveshaft's, dampers, door seals and headlinings, working with the supplier quality teams to achieve key project milestones.

Fast tracked to Quality Project Leader within the Quality Development Division, I was responsible for the development of quality maturation plans and developing new strategies for high quality products globally to achieve and exceed the customers ever increasing expectations for both quality and reliability. Achieving these targets required cross departmental interaction to ensure quality targets were achieved from the prototype trial phases through to mass production. This included past problem analysis and the development of new strategies to countermeasure the warranty and in-house concerns.

Customer Experience Specialist - Heavyline at JCB

January 2011 - April 2011 (4 months)

Reason for leaving – temporary position only.

Duties included:

- Project management of a high profile IT/engineering project
- Regular presentations with senior management reviewing project status
- Project implementation including personnel training

Hired for my technical knowledge, I was required to help manage and develop a new high profile project within JCB. This position gave me an introduction into project management and presentation skills at senior management level. The position also required me to develop my skills in people management, working as a trainer I was required to present the project status and function to the dealers and their engineers and train them in the use of the software.

Customer Service Engineer at Parkinson's harness technology

May 2008 - September 2008 (5 months)

Reason for leaving - Summer placement

Duties included:

- Developing a working, hands-on understanding of how a vehicle harness is manufactured
- Working closely with the testing team to develop faster and more efficient test boards
- Developing a strong working relationship with the customer to ensure the needs of both parties are met where ever possible

Specialising in wiring harnesses for a number of major manufacturers including leading plant and commercials manufacturers my role was to produce and test wiring harnesses (using advanced technology to produce the highest quality wiring harnesses and to fault find any concerns as quickly and efficiently as possible).

My role quickly moved into the designing of new wiring harnesses including customer interaction to achieve a product that met the expectations of both parties.

Skills & Expertise

Vehicle Maintenance

AutoCAD

Solidworks

Hydraulics

Pneumatics

Machining

Kaizen

5S

Root Cause Analysis

Six Sigma

Catia V5

Initial Quality Study (IQS)

Product Quality Study (PQS)

Manufacturing

Catia

Quality Assurance

Engineering

Automotive

Continuous Improvement

Supplier Quality

Project Planning

TQM

FMEA

Manufacturing Engineering

Lean Manufacturing

APQP

PPAP

Automotive Engineering

Management

SPC

Quality Management

Courses

Certificate of Competency, Welding & Fabrication

Coventry Welding Workshop

Mig Welding

Oxyacetylene Cutting

Bachelor of Engineering (BEng), Automotive Systems Engineering

The University of Wolverhampton

BEng Automotive Systems Engineering

C&G Technical Certification - Level 3, Electrical Installation and High Voltage Applications

Training in Electrical

C&G 2377-22 Portable Appliance Testing

C&G 2382-12 17th Edition Wiring Regulations

C&G 2365 Diploma in Electrical Installations Level 2

C&G 2365 Diploma in Electrical Installations Level 3

C&G 2394/2395 Initial & Periodic Inspection, Testing

& Condition Reporting

Master of Science (MSc), Data Communication Networks

Aston University

MSc Data Communication Networks

Certificate of Competency, Construction Trades

Coventry Building Workshop

Bricklaying

Plastering

Plumbing

Bathroom Fitting

Joinery/Carpentry

Kitchen Fitting

Tiling

BTEC National Diploma, Operations and Maintenance Engineering

Boston College

BTEC National Diploma in Operations & Maintenance

Engineering

NVQ 2 Performing Engineering Operations

C&G Level 3 2D CAD

C&G Level 3 3D CAD

A - E - Quality Project Leader

Honda of the UK Manufacturing Ltd.

Advanced Driver Training

Known Consigner Training

Independent Coursework

TeamCenter

Catia Fundamentals

Education

Training in Electrical

C&G Technical Certification - Level 3, Electrical Installation and High Voltage Applications, 2015 - 2016

Grade: Pass

Aston University

Master of Science (MSc), Data Communication Networks, 2014 - 2016

Grade: TBC

Coventry Building Workshop

Certificate of Competency, Construction Trades, 2015 - 2015

Grade: Pass

Coventry Welding Workshop

Certificate of Competency, Welding & Fabrication, 2014 - 2014

Grade: Pass

The University of Wolverhampton

Bachelor of Engineering (BEng), Automotive Systems Engineering, 2007 - 2010

Grade: 2:1

Boston College

BTEC National Diploma, Operations and Maintenance Engineering, 2005 - 2007

Grade: Triple Distinction

The Giles School & Sixth Form Centre

GCSE study, 2000 - 2005

Grade: A-C

Interests

I have long had a passion for engineering and particularly in the automotive and defence industries including motor sport of almost all varieties. My interests have also taken me down the route of volunteering as first aider for St John Ambulance where I act as first aider and also as a trainer. I also enjoy a number of activities such as horse riding and motor biking. In the interest of self development I have also recently started to develop my knowledge of foreign languages.

Languages

English

Spanish - Basic

Volunteer Experience

Advanced first aider/member trainer at St John Ambulance

September 2011 - Present

Originally trained as a first aider my progression quickly moved me in to advanced first aid (including medical gases and defibrillators).

My recent involvement found me becoming qualified and trained to teach others in first aid.

James Appleby

EDS Project Engineer at Draexlmaier UK

james.appleby1989@gmail.com



Contact James on LinkedIn